Guide to the Manchester Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Albums, 1697/98 Feb 8; Series I
  - Extract from the register of Resolutions of the States General of the United Netherlands, (a reply to the memorial of the Sieur de Quiros, to be sent also to the Comte de Briord), disclaiming any warlike intentions which might have been inferred from the position of their troops in certain places in the Netherlands. (In French. See 19), 1701 Feb 9 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - The same in Dutch, with two additional sentences. (A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 308), 1701 Feb 9 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Copy of the First Memorial of the Comte d'Avaux to the States General, expressing the desire of the King of France that peace should be maintained, and accompanied by a copy of a Letter of Credence (dated Feb. 2) to him as Ambassador Extraordinary. (In French. Translations are printed in Cole's Memoirs, pp. 311-312) The Hague, 1701 Feb 13 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Copy of a Memorial of the Sieur de Geldermalsen, Envoy Extraordinary of the States General to the King of Great Britain, announcing that the States thought it necessary to proceed to the recognition of the Duc d'Anjou as King of Spain, and that they wished to act in concert with his Britannic Majesty, upon whose assistance they relied in the event of an attack upon them by France. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 320) (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - The E of M to the States General, giving an account of an interview with M. de Torcy (on the subject of the reply of the States General to the Sieur de Quiros), and of the pacific assurances then received. (In French. Copy. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 312) Paris, 1701 Feb 18 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Extract from the Register of Resolutions of the States General of the United Netherlands, being the decision to inform the Comte d'Avaux that the States were willing to acknowledge the Duc d'Anjou as King of Spain, and hoped the King of France would consequently withdraw his troops from the Spanish Netherlands. (In French. An English translation "out of Dutch" is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 316), 1701 Feb 21 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - The States General of the United Netherlands to the E of M, informing him that he had decided to recognise the Duc d'Anjou as King of Spain, and that the Sieur de Heemskerk would deliver the decision to the French Court. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 316) The Hague, 1701 Feb 22 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Copy of a letter from the States General to the King of France, in which they acknowledge the Duc d'Anjou as King of Spain, and express their congratulations upon his accession. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 318), 1701 Feb 22 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Extract from the Register of Resolutions of the States General of the United Netherlands, being the resolution upon which the last-mentioned letter was founded. (In French. An English translation "out of Dutch" is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 318), 1701 Feb 22 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Copy of instructions to Alexander Stanhope, Esq., as Envoy Exraordinary to the States General, for the purpose of negotiating a treaty for the withdrawal of the French troops from the Spanish Netherlands. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 332) Kensington, 1700/01 Feb 25 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Copy of the reply of the King of France to a letter addressed to him by the States General. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 324) Versailles, 1701 Mar 3 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Copy of a letter from the E of M to the States General, giving some particulars of an interview with M. de Torcy, who had said that the French troops would be withdrawn from the posts in the Netherlands as soon as the King of Spain was in a position to provide for their defence himself. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 325) Paris, 1701 Mar 4 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Copy of a Memorial of the Comte de Briord (the French Ambassador) to the States General, on the Occasion of taking his departure for the re- establishment of his health. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 341) The Hague, 1701 Mar 22 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Extract from the Register of Resolutions of the States General of the United Netherlands, being the decision to communicate (in concert with Mr. Stanhope, the British Envoy Extraordinary) to the Comte d'Avaux, the articles of a projected treaty having for its object the withdrawal of the French troops from the Spanish Netherlands, and a general settlement which would be acceptable to all the parties to the Treaty of Partition from which the King of France had been withdrawn. (French. An English translation "out of Dutch" is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 341), 1701 Mar 22 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Propositions delivered to the Comte d'Avaux by Mr. Stanhope at the first conference with him. They are of the same purport as the document last mentioned. (In French. 6 pages. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 339), 1700 Mar 22 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Extract from the Register of Resolutions of the States General of the United Netherlands, relating to the sitting at which was received, from the Deputies of Foreign Affairs, a report of their conference with M. d'Avaux, who had told them it was necessary he should consult his master upon the subject of the proposal that the English should hold Niuport and Ostend, and the States certain other places as "places de sureté." (In French. An English translation "out of Dutch" is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 343), 1701 Mar 22 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Copy of a letter from Phillip V, King of Spain, to William III of England, announcing that he had obtained possession of the Spanish dominions, and expressing hopes that he might enjoy the friendship of the English King. (In Latin. A translation, of all but Phillip's full style and title, is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 334) Buen Retiro, 1701 Mar 24 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Message of William III to the House of Commons, informing them of the apparent termination of negotiations between the States General and the King of France, and of the application made by the States General for assistance from England, according to the terms of the treaty of 3rd March 1677. (Printed in the Commons' journals, XIII, 402) Kensington, 1701 Mar 31 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Abstract of the proposition of Count Schlick, General in the Emperor's Army, to the Electors of Cologne, asking them to aid the Emperor in the assertion of his claim to the Spanish monarchy, in the event of a rupture among the powers. It is followed by an abstract of the unfavourable reply of the Electors. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 356) Bonn, 1701 Apr 10 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Copy of a letter from William III to Phillip V, of Spain, congratulating the latter upon his accession, and expressing good will, and hopes of lasting friendship. (In Latin. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 370) Kensington, 1701 Apr 17 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Extract from the Register of Resolutions of the States General of the United Netherlands, being the decision to represent to the Comte d'Avaux their anxiety to secure the general peace of Europe as well as their own interests. (In French. An English translation "out of Dutch" is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 371), 1701 May 2 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Extract from the Register of Resolutions of the States General of the United Netherlands, being the decision to communicate to Mr. Stanhope the refusal of the Comte d'Avaux to consent to his presence, as representing British interests, at any conference in which the matters discussed related to the States General, though he might be present "pour seconder les interêts de cet Estat." (In French. This and the preceding document are fastened together, and the dates are reversed in their endorsements. An English translation "out of Dutch" is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 372), 1701 May 3 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Message of William III to the House of Commons, communicating to them a letter from the States General, and representing that the safety of England and the very existence of Holland were in danger. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 384) Kensington, 1701 May 8 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Copy of a letter from the States General to William III, to the effect that they regarded the interests of their country and of England as inseparable, though the Comte d'Avaux had objected to the presence of Mr. Stanhope as representative of British interests at any conference affecting the interests of the States, that they perceived in his conduct a desire on the part of France to put an end to the negotiations, and that they were in urgent need of British succours, as there were already important movements of French troops. (In French. Seven closely written pages. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 379) The Hague, 1701 May 13 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Copy of a Memorial of the Emperor's Envoy [Count Wratislaw], to William III, representing the alleged dangers threatening Europe, from the ambition of the King of France, and requesting aid in accordance with the treaty of 1689. (In Latin. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 385) London, 1701 May 22/11 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Extract from the Resolutions of the Cirle of Suabia, being a reply to the Envoy Extraordinary of France (who had offered explanations respecting the march of French troops into Alsace, etc.) to the effect that Suabia and the whole Empire would be compelled to take up arms in defence, should any State belonging to, or dependent on the Empire be touched. It is stated, at the foot, that the French Envoy took his leave a few days after the receipt of this reply. (In French) Ulm, 1701 May 28 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Abstract of the Secret Articles of the Treaty concluded with Denmark by England and the States General. (Printed, with some verbal variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 393) Copenhagen, 1701 Jun 15 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Abstract of the Treaty between England, Denmark, and the States General. (pp. 5. Printed, with some verbal variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 391), 1701 Jun 15 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Abstract of a Convention between England, Sweden, and the States General. (Six short articles. 1 p.) The Hague, 1701 Sep 26/Oct 7 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Abstract of the treaty between England, the Empire, and the States General. (Printed, with some verbal variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 416) The Hague, 1701 Sep 7 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Copy of the letter of the E of M, announcing his recall upon the recognition of the Pretender by the King of France, and a copy of M. de Torcy's reply. (In French. Translations are printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 426), 1701 Oct 2 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - [M. Vroese or Vroesen] to the E of M, mentioning the correspondence of a Jesuit in London (Father Plaud) with the French Court, and some military movements in Italy, whither the King of Spain had found it necessary to send reinforcements of his best troops. (In French) Paris, 1702 Jan 7 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - The Abbé Melani to the E of M, cautioning him against "Milord de Maleborath" [Marlborough], who had sent to make enquiries respecting the Earl's delay in leaving Paris, and giving an account of the hardships endured by the mother and wife of the Count Bosselli in the Bastille, where the Governor had made them suffer for the Count's escape. (In French. 7 pages) Paris, 1702 Jan 4 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - M. Schonenberg to Mr. Secretary Vernon, giving an account of the illness of the King of Spain, and of the recall (at the instigation of France) of certain officers from the Spanish army in Italy, who were supposed to be too favourably inclined to Austrian interests. He suggested, in a postscript, that when the time came for his own recall he should have Letters of Credence to the King of Portugal, who might be persuaded to act as the Allies desired. (In French) Madrid, 1702 Jan 11 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - M. Schonenberg to Mr. Secretary Vernon (but according to the endorsement "sent open to Lord Manchester.") He describes his successful efforts to protect the interests of British traders in Spain, the difficulty with which the Governor of Cadiz was restrained from firing at British frigates driven under the citadel by a violent storm, and the lethargy with which the Spanish nation abandoned itself to French influence. He had been questioned on the subject of the removal of the Arms of England from his house, and had not scrupled to give the real reason. (See vol. 6, No. 687, 53.) The French King had given assurance to the Spanish Ambassador that he would do everything in his power in support of his engagements, though not in a position to do as much as he desired. (In French. pp. 6) Madrid, 1702 Jan 11 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - M. Jurieu to the E of M. He and his co-religionists looked upon the King of England as a man chosen by God to abate the pride of tyrants, preserve the liberty of Europe, and spread the true religion. The King of England had quite as much right to uphold the Edict of Nantes as the King of France to interfere in the matter of the succession to the English throne. Letters had been sent to the principal Ministers of the State to the effect that God had not blessed previous treaties, because His interests had been altogether forgotten in them. The Earl was implored, on that and other accounts, to press upon the attention of the King the interests of Protestants abroad. Memorials on the subject had been sent to Mr. Secretary Vernon. (In French. 7 pages) Also postscript to the same, written on separate paper, so that while the letter could be shown to various persons, the "petites affaires" between Jurieu and the Earl would be kept to themselves. This relates to the amount and mode of remittance of money to be paid to Jurieu, and to M. Caillaud. The latter, it seems, undertook the "correspondences de France," but not the "correspondences de Flandre." The details had been arranged by Mr. Blathwayt and Mr. Vernon. The remittances, however, were not sent quite in accordance with the wishes of the "correspondents." (In French. 4 pages) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Memorandum relating to the affairs of Lithuania, including the death of the young Sapieha. (In French) Warsaw, 1702 Jan 20 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - M. Martine to [the E of M], promising to keep him informed of events which might occur at Paris, but pointing out that it would be necessary to take some precautions. Martine could not depend on any official position to enable him to send his letters openly, because he could not claim it on the ground of his employment in the service of the Republic of Geneva, and his employment in the service of the Court of Cassell would cease with the expected rupture. (In French) Paris, 1702 Jan 27 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - M. Schonenberg to Mr. Secretary Vernon, on the affairs of the Court of Spain. (In French. pp. 6) Madrid, 1702 Jan 25 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - M. Schonenberg to Mr. Secretary Vernon, referring again to the financial embarrassments of Spain, mentioning the delay of the British ships of war at Cadiz through stress of weather, and the rumour from France that the King of Spain was to command in Italy in person, and touching on some minor details of Spanish affairs. (In French. 6 closely written pages.) Madrid, 1702 Jan 26 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Unsigned paper (possible sent by Martine, though not in his handwriting), giving information of the decision of the Council and King in France in favour of the departure of the King of Spain for Naples. The latter would probably go on afterwards to the Milanese, if, indeed, there were not found insuperable objections to the whole project at the last moment. Much surprise had been caused by the ready vote of 5,000,000 £ to the King in England. Various rumours which had reached the writer are mentioned, and among them one that the Princess of Denmark was pregnant. (In French.) Paris, 1702 Jan 27 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - John Cole to the E of M, on the affairs of Lithuania, where the families of Sapieha and Oginski had become reconciled (thus opening the way to peace between Sweden and Poland) on the negotiations of the Emperor with the Elector of Cologne, and on the warlike preparations in the Netherlands, where the Resolutions taken in England had given much encouragement. Amsterdam, 1702 Jan 27 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - M. Plantamour to the E of M, congratulating him on his appointment as First Secretary of State, and mentioning enclosure. (In French) Berlin, 1702 Jan 28 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Enclosure, giving some particulars of news lately received at Berlin. (In French) Berlin, 1702 Jan 28 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - M. Martine to the E of M, suggesting that his letter should, for the sake of secrecy, be directed, under cover, to some person in trade. A little judicious expenditure might aid in the discovery of what was going on at Court. M. Martine was not in any way actuated by a regard for his own interest, and he would prefer to receive whatever the Earl might be pleased to give him, not in one sum, but as an annual salary. (In French) Paris, 1702 Jan 31 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Paper (unsigned, and possible sent by M. Martine, but not in his handwriting), on French military affairs, and the projected expedition of the King of Spain to Naples and the Milanese, on the news from various parts of Europe, and especially from Italy, and the alarm excited in France by the attitude of England. (In French) Paris, 1702 Jan 31 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - M. Schonenberg to Mr. Secretary Vernon, giving an account of the alarm felt in Spain by the projected voyage of the King to Naples, of the refusal of the traders of Madrid to make a special contribution to meet emergencies, and of the hopeless condition of Spain in general. He mentions enclosure of a copy of a letter from the King of France to the King of Spain. (In French) Madrid, 1702 Feb 9 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - G. Stepney to the E of M, expressing hopes of the success of the Imperialists in Italy, and of the accession of the Archduke to the Crown of Naples, and asking for the Earl's influence that he might be appointed to bear the King's congratulations upon that event. Count Mansfeldt, the Austrian "President of War," had always lived in good correspondence with the Duke of Savoy, and still hoped he might "play his old game and change sides." It would therefore be expedient "so to manage Count Maffei as to keep open a door for reconcilement to which the Duke's natural love of change would contribute." Jordan was "like to go out in a snuff at Paris," as his master's "volatile spirit was at last fixed in favour of the Allies." Perhaps Bavaria would do the same after the vigorous resolutions of the English Parliament, which had inspired great confidence in Austria. An enclosure is mentioned. Vienna, 1702 Feb 5 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Memorandum (endorsed "Stepney,") giving particulars of the Austrian troops destined for the expedition to Naples, against which the Nuncio, Prince Eugene, and the Envoy of Modena had remonstrated, as calculated to weaken the Imperial forces elsewhere. A draft treaty between the King of Poland and the Emperor for the supply of troops to the latter had been brought from Warsaw. Vienna, 1702 Feb 5 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - M. Schonenberg to Mr. Secretary Vernon, showing how completely Spain was under the influence of France, even to matters of ecclesiastical patronage, and how it would be through that influence that the King would set out for Naples, and giving some financial, military, and naval details. (In French. 7 closely written pages.) Madrid, 1702 Feb 8 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - "J.G." to "Mr. Hainning, at the Rt. Hon. the Earl of Portland's lodgings," giving an account of the news which had reached Paris of the surprise of Cremona, effected by Prince Eugene, and of his subsequent defeat by the French, though he had retained Marshal Villeroy as his prisoner. Paris, 1702 Feb 10 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Alexander Stanhope to the E of M, expressing satisfaction with the great public spirit displayed by the Dutch, and their readiness for war. He touches on the humiliation of Marshal Villeroy, and the various probabilities of the political and military situation. Lord Albemarle had arrived. The Hague, 1701/02 Feb 10/21 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - M. Hervart to the E of M, on the attitude of the various Swiss Cantons with respect to the recognition of the Duc d'Anjou as King of Spain, and the efforts of the Marquis de Puisieulx, the French Ambassador, to obtain it. (In French) Bern, 1702 Feb 11 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Etienne Caillaud to the E of M, informing him that the Comte de Breuille and a person named La Roche were supposed to have embarked at the Brill for London. It was expected that the address of La Roche in London could be obtained from his wife. The Earl was thanked for his protection of Caillaud's brother. The return of M. Coetlogon to Brest, without the galleons, which remained at Vera Cruz, would seriously derange the finances of Louis XIV. (In French) Rotterdam, 1702 Feb 21 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Unsigned memorandum (by M. Hervart?) on the attitude of the Swiss Cantons in relation to Austria and to France. They had decided that they would not congratulate the Duc d'Anjou [on his accession to the throne of Spain]. The Marquis de Puisieulx had represented the affair at Cremona as advantageous to the French, and had, in consequence, been compared to the "Cuckold in the Comedy," who was beaten and content. (In French) Baden, 1702 Feb 18 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - M. Schonenberg to Mr. Secretary Vernon, on British subjects who had become naturalised in Spain, especially Francis Archer, a banker, said to be a violent Papist and a partisan of France, and a zealous supporter of the party opposed to "the rights of the legitimate succession in the Protestant line." (In French) Madrid, 1702 Feb 22 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - M. Schonenberg to Mr. Secretary Vernon, giving an account of the suspicions entertained in Spain that the Spanish King's intended voyage to Naples might be followed by his abandonment of Spain for the throne of Naples and Sicily alone, of the discontent general among all ranks in Spain, and of the difficulty in finding money for the public service. M. Schonenberg maintains the accuracy of the details in this and previous letters of the helpless condition of Spain, though the reports of some persons, and even of some consuls, might cause a different impression. The partisans of France were striving to inspire confidence in expectation of the return of the Mexican fleet. Their boasts would probably come to nothing, but the allies would do well to make a demonstration with promptitude. (In French. 7 pages) Madrid, 1702 Feb 22 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Memorandum (unsigned) on the proceedings of the Swiss Cantons, including their resolution to accede to the demand of the Emperor for a levy of troops. The Protestant Cantons had decided that they would not recognise the Duc d'Anjou as King of Spain; the others held the question ad referendum. (In French) Baden, 1702 Feb 22 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - M. Hervart to the E of M, mentioning difficulties caused by the demand of the Canton of Zurich to nominate the Colonel of one of the regiments demanded by the Emperor from the Swiss. (In French) Bern, 1702 Feb 22 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - M. Hervart to the E of M, expressing an opinion that the Swiss Cantons would remain firm in their resolve not to recognise the Duc d'Anjou as King of Spain. (In French) Bern, 1702 Feb 25 (Box 8, Folder 29)